<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A case of conscience whether a nonconformist, who hath not taken the Oxford Oath, may come to live at London, or at any corporate town, or within five miles of it, and yet be a good Christian : stated briefly, and published in reference to what is offered to the contrary, in a book intituled, A friendly debate betwixt a confirmist and a nonconformist : together with animadversions on a new book, entituled, Ecclesiastical polity, the general heads and substance whereof are taken under consideration : as also a peaceable dissertation, by way of composition with some late papers, entituled, Liberty of conscience, in order to the determining the magistrates power in matters of religion.</title>
            <author>Humfrey, John, 1621-1719.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1669</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 87 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45126</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3673</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16379</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12859533</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12859533</idno>
            <idno type="VID">94656</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45126)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94656)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 985:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A case of conscience whether a nonconformist, who hath not taken the Oxford Oath, may come to live at London, or at any corporate town, or within five miles of it, and yet be a good Christian : stated briefly, and published in reference to what is offered to the contrary, in a book intituled, A friendly debate betwixt a confirmist and a nonconformist : together with animadversions on a new book, entituled, Ecclesiastical polity, the general heads and substance whereof are taken under consideration : as also a peaceable dissertation, by way of composition with some late papers, entituled, Liberty of conscience, in order to the determining the magistrates power in matters of religion.</title>
                  <author>Humfrey, John, 1621-1719.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>31 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1669.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to John Humfrey.  Cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. 31.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Patrick, Simon, 1626-1707. --  Friendly debate between a conformist and a non-conformist.</term>
               <term>Parker, Samuel, 1640-1688. --  Discourse of ecclesiastical politie.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church polity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Liberty of conscience --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:94656:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:94656:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Caſe of Conſcience, Whether a <hi>Nonconformist,</hi> who hath not taken the <hi>Oxford</hi> Oath, may come to live at <hi>London,</hi> or at any Corporate-Town, or within five miles of it, and yet be <hi>a good Chriſtian?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Stated briefly, and publiſhed,</hi> In reference to what is offered to the contrary, in a Book intituled, <hi>A Friendly Debate</hi> betwixt a <hi>Conformiſt</hi> and a <hi>Nonconformiſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Together with Animadverſions</hi> on a new Book, entituled, <hi>Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Polity;</hi> the general Heads and Subſtance whereof are taken under conſideration.</p>
            <p>AS ALSO <hi>A Peaceable Diſſertation.</hi> By way of <hi>Compoſition</hi> with ſome late <hi>Papers,</hi> enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled, <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> in order to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termining the Magiſtrates Power in matters of Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Year. 1669.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:94656:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:94656:2"/>
            <head>The Caſe.</head>
            <p>BEing importuned to make ſome <hi>Animadverſions</hi> on the <hi>Friendly Debate,</hi> I had finiſhed ſeveral ſheets, and intended but two or three more, when I was certified that an <hi>Anſwer</hi> was in the Preſs and prevented me; which together with the unliklihood of getting an <hi>Imprimatur</hi> for it when I had done, hath given me a <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſedeas</hi> at preſent to what remains; and made me think what I cannot do in the <hi>whole,</hi> may be effected perhaps in <hi>parts.</hi> I ſhall begin there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore upon this Point, which ſeems to me the moſt material of any in that Book to be conſidered, both in regard of the loſs the moſt are at what to Anſwer, and the neceſſity of their ſatisfaction, ſeeing if they act not <hi>in Faith</hi> in what they do, they cannot acquit themſelves from <hi>ſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>How can that man be a Miniſter of Christ, who is diſobedient to his So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign? And that, even in thoſe things wherein Christ and his Laws are not concerned. The Law of the Land forbids the</hi> Nonconformiſt <hi>to live in</hi> London, <hi>or within five miles of it. But that is not repugnant to the Command of Christ, and therefore he is not a good Subject, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly not a good Chriſtian; much leſs ſuch a Miniſter of Chriſt as he ought to be.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this one paſſage in that Book, I do take my conjecture of the Author, to be a Perſon happy in his Expreſſion, and ingenuous in his Diſpoſition, rather than deep in the things he delivers, or ſtudious and reflective on thoſe more <hi>Removes</hi> than one he ought to ſee, who will play ſuch a Game as this, with all his fellows at once, that are in the Miniſtry, of a contrary party. To bind the obſervation of all human Laws (not ſinful in the fact) upon the Conſcience without diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is the doing he does not know what. An unmerciful determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion! which being paſſed too upon that particular <hi>Oxford</hi> Act, hath drawn from the reſt, this <hi>Animadverſion</hi> (as it lyes there) out of my Papers.</p>
            <p>I am ſorry that any Perſon of ſo much candour, latitude, and inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity, as I believe the Writer of this Book to have, ſhould be ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind to his Brethren, ſo unconſcionably untender (to expreſs the thing as it is) as to account, That no man who tranſgreſſes an Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (ſuch as for the <hi>Nonconformiſt</hi> to come within five miles of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi>)
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:94656:3"/>can be a good Chriſtian. Alas! how preciſe are ſome men as to the Law of the <hi>Land,</hi> who are yet ſo angry at others for being ſtrict to the Laws of <hi>God?</hi> But does this Reverend Perſon indeed think that every tranſgreſſion of a Statute of the Realm is no leſs than a <hi>deadly ſin!</hi> Or dare he wilfully <hi>judge</hi> here, any otherwiſe than himſelf would be <hi>judged?</hi> What then if a man ſhall-live and die in the breach of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Statutes, which he knows, and yet thinks nothing of it, muſt ſuch a one be certainly damned? What if a man ſhould live and die in a Cottage of his own erecting, that hath not four Acres of Ground to it? Or may a man live and die in a wilful known ſin, without Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and be ſaved? <hi>Too rigorous were it</hi> (ſayes Mr. <hi>Hooker,</hi> that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood himſelf here no doubt a little better) <hi>that the breach of every Law ſhould be ſo held; a Mean there is between theſe extremities, if ſo be we could find it out.</hi> I muſt confeſs I have not read any, to my remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, that have ventured on the chalking out this <hi>Mean</hi> that I ſhould gather ſatisfaction from it; ſo that I muſt content my ſelf with my own Sentiments, which I ſhall readily deliver, being glad at my heart if I can unlooſe any <hi>burden,</hi> which many that are tender may be apt to <hi>bind</hi> on their <hi>Conſciences,</hi> when ſome that tye the ſame, would be loth to touch them with their <hi>little fingers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Magiſtrate I account with the Apoſtle, is the <hi>Miniſter of God</hi> for the Peoples <hi>good.</hi> If he command in order to that end, I think his Commands ought to be obeyed, not only for <hi>fear</hi> of his Sword, but for <hi>Conſcience ſake:</hi> But if he command any thing for the Peoples hurt, or that which evidently is not for their good, I think his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand (if the matter be not ſin) is yet to be obeyed for <hi>Wrath ſake,</hi> and ſo not to be <hi>contemned;</hi> but I think not any obligation lyes on the <hi>Conſcience,</hi> if it can be avoided without contempt or ſcandal, that it ſhould be <hi>done.</hi> We muſt diſtinguiſh here between the authority that reſides in the <hi>Perſon,</hi> and the authority of this or that his <hi>particular Command.</hi> I do apprehend that when any <hi>Command</hi> or Law does require <hi>that,</hi> which is <hi>Morally</hi> or <hi>Civilly</hi> evil, every ſuch Command or Law, is really diveſted of authority, and ſo may be left undone without breach on a man's Conſcience; yet if a man be brought to queſtion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it, he muſt ſuffer, becauſe the authority which reſides ſtill in the <hi>Perſon</hi> muſt be ſubmitted to, as to the <hi>Ordinance of God.</hi> He muſt not <hi>reſist,</hi> that is expreſs; and rather than <hi>reſist,</hi> he muſt <hi>ſuffer;</hi> whereas if he could avoid it without <hi>reſiſtance,</hi> he was not bound in good earneſt, either to <hi>do,</hi> or <hi>ſuffer.</hi> Where we are not obliged <hi>ad agendum, ad pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiendum,</hi> ſayes <hi>Grotius, tum demum ubi poena evitari niſi vi oppoſita non poteſt. De Imp. ſum. pot. circa ſac.</hi> p. 98.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:94656:3"/>
            <p>The reaſon of this at the bottom lyes here, and is firm. <hi>Power</hi> in the <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> or <hi>Civil power,</hi> which is the ground of ſubjection, does not lye in <hi>might,</hi> ſtrength, or force, but in <hi>right. Poteſtas</hi> (ſay Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal writers) is <hi>jus imperandi.</hi> This <hi>right</hi> in the nature of the thing muſt ariſe from the <hi>Grant</hi> or <hi>Will</hi> of the ſupream Lord, which is God, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out whoſe Will (or that Grant, or Charter, which is an act of his will) no Power can be derived from any. Now that <hi>grant</hi> or <hi>will</hi> of God which conſtitutes any to Rule, or to be his <hi>Miniſter,</hi> being for the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples <hi>weale</hi> (He is the <hi>Miniſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f God for our weale,</hi> ſayes the text;) it muſt follow that whatſoever <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> not indeed for the Peoples <hi>weale;</hi> the Magiſtrate is not to command, becauſe it is God's will be commands only for their <hi>weale.</hi> And if he do command any matter that is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, that Command hath no Authority as to the <hi>Conſcience</hi> at all, as being without the warrant of God's <hi>will.</hi> This is ſuch Doctrine, which is plain, bottom'd and irrefragable; <hi>He is the Miniſter of God for thy good,</hi> ſaith St. Paul, <hi>otherwiſe he is not God's Miniſter, and hath to other purpoſes none of God's power;</hi> Dr. <hi>Taylor</hi> in his Caſes, <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 35. <hi>Quod neceſſariam non habet conjunctionem cum fine publici commodi non potest praecipi lege huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> ſayes <hi>Suarez</hi> from the Schools.</p>
            <p>One difficulty onely there is, which is this: Who ſhall judge whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Law be for the peoples <hi>Weal,</hi> or not? I anſwer, The Magiſtrate muſt judge as to the <hi>making</hi> the Law, and we muſt judge as to our <hi>obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience</hi> to it: My Reaſon I give as readily, Becauſe God hath made e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man the Judge of his own Actions, and conſequently of all the Circumſtances, whether they are agreeable, or not agreeable to his will, for his forbearance, or doing of them: So that it is not according to the reſolution of any others Conſcience, but of his own, or the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Private Diſcretion,</hi> he ſhall be juſtified, or not juſtified in his walking before him. Let a Law then be promulgated wherein a man is concerned, I thus determine: If he deal uprightly, that is, as a <hi>Christian,</hi> (to uſe induſtriouſly this perſons word) and in his Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence does judge that the Law is <hi>good;</hi> I mean good for the general, (whether their ſpiritual or temporal good) I do apprehend he is obliged in Conſcience to the obeying that Law, (at leaſt ſo far as his particular obedience is conducive to that good) though the keeping of it other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe be to his own diſadvantage or private loſs. If he judges it <hi>not good,</hi> I do ſuppoſe he may do well in prudence to be wasy, and do per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps as others do, and not run himſelf into harm's way: But really if he obſerves it not, he is to make no Conſcience of it, as if the thing offended God, whether he does it, or leaves it undone. And here is
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:94656:4"/>that very <hi>Mean</hi> indeed it ſelf, for ought I know, <hi>quod deſideratur.</hi> To wit, That the Laws or Commands of the Magiſtrate (even in political and indifferent things) does no leſs than <hi>bind the Conſcience,</hi> when he is the Executioner of <hi>Gods-Will:</hi> But though the <hi>outward man</hi> (out of the caſe of ſin) may be bound, if you will; the <hi>Conſcience</hi> cannot be obliged, and ought to be ſtill kept free, when he is the Executioner onely of his <hi>own. Humans Laws</hi> (ſays the fore-mentioned excellent Doctor and Biſhop) <hi>bind the Conſcience of the Subjects, but yet give place to juſt and charitable Cauſes: Whi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> competent and ſufficient, is not expreſly and minutely declared, but <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to be defined by the modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and prudence of a good man<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know not how this Author may receive this, from whom I expect more ingenuity than from many others; that is, to yield to ſecond con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations: But methinks, if he had not thought at firſt (when he wrote) of any thing beſides, he might at leaſt have conſidered that there be Laws, which of themſelves grow out of date; and that it is not Time ſo much that brings on them their decay, as the apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of them to be unreaſonable, unfit, or unprofitable to the Land. When a Law therefore is by general <hi>tasit</hi> allowance and practiſe of the Nation, had no longer in regard, it is to be accounted as <hi>virtually obſolete,</hi> and ſo it binds not. There was a Law made this Parliament about <hi>Carts</hi> and <hi>Waggons,</hi> for the better keeping the <hi>High-wayes;</hi> which being found quickly inconvenient to the <hi>Waggoners,</hi> and unanſwerable we may ſuppoſe to the <hi>End,</hi> it was ſcarce a Month or two, but they heard no more of it. I will put a Caſe now of Conſcience to this Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; Suppoſe a man whoſe living conſiſts in his Waggon, and unleſs he puts more Horſes in his Team, in his coming up to <hi>London,</hi> than this Law will allow, he muſt give off his Trade, or be undone. I ask, What ſhall this fellow do? By the Doctrine of this Book, for ought I can ſee, he can be <hi>no good Subject, and conſequently no good Chriſtian,</hi> if he goes on. I will ask again; What thinks the Author of thoſe that die and are <hi>buried</hi> in the <hi>iniquity</hi> of <hi>Linnen?</hi> Whether the Women ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally of this Nation, who cannot abide to have the <hi>dead</hi> wrapt in <hi>Flannel;</hi> but being uſed ſo much to controul their <hi>Husbands at home,</hi> will not be ruled by <hi>both Houſes,</hi> to do any otherwiſe herein than what they think is <hi>handſomest</hi> for all them, are in capacity, without their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment in this point, to be ſaved? For my own part, I think verily the latter of theſe Laws being intended, &amp; tending directly to the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular good of the Nation, it ought in Conſcience to have been kept; yet ſeeing the very <hi>humour</hi> only of the Women hath diſcountenanc'd
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:94656:4"/>it, ſo that in the general uſage it is annull'd; I dare not ſay that any man does ſin, that obſerves it not. I dare not ſay that <hi>Wife</hi> can be <hi>no good Chriſtian</hi> that buries her <hi>Husband</hi> in his <hi>ſhirt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the Act it ſelf of <hi>Oxford,</hi> I cannot paſs methinks, without the obſervation of God's providence, toward that great Perſon, who in his Speech that Seſſion, ſo induſtriouſly declared himſelf the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigner: <hi>Since the Parliament at</hi> Oxford, <hi>it hath been viſible</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>that my credit hath been very little.</hi> He who had contrived the Baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of others from <hi>their houſes</hi> by that Act, leaves this paſſage in his Letter, at his own <hi>departure</hi> out of the <hi>Realm.</hi> But though he might be forgetful in his proſperity, and unſenſible of thoſe inconveniencies which he was bringing thoſe into, who had done nothing againſt him; Yet do not thou, O God, for all he hath done againſt thee, deprive him in his adverſity of the favour of <hi>thy Houſe,</hi> nor forget to bring his ſoul out of trouble, when thou ſhalt firſt have brought it in, with the ſenſe of what has been amiſs, in ſuch doings.</p>
            <p>For the Oath impoſed, as the condition of the <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> lawful coming to this City, or any other Corporation, by that <hi>Oxford</hi> Act; there are the <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> Exceptions againſt it propoſed in that Book entituled, <hi>A Defence of the Propoſition.</hi> If the Author of this <hi>Debate,</hi> or that ingenious Perſon, who (they ſay) is writing ſomething a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Policy,</hi> for the juſtifying preſent Impoſitions; or that worthy Perſon his aſſociate, who is particularly engaged to it, can Anſwer them, let them try. This I muſt ſay, that I ſuppoſe the chief of thoſe things which ſtick in good earneſt upon the ſober <hi>Nonconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mist,</hi> and which others do not, or dare not ſpeak out, are there offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, againſt that <hi>Oath,</hi> and againſt <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity.</hi> If they ſhall ſet down the words fairly and candidly, and anſwer them ſatisfactorily, they ſhall do well: But if they <hi>do not</hi> (after this notice) the world ſhall account indeed they <hi>cannot;</hi> and what they ſay otherwiſe, muſt ſignifie nothing. I will conclude with <hi>Grotius,</hi> and return to my Theme; <hi>Leges humanae vim obligandi tum demum habent, ſi latae ſint ad huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num modum, non ſi onus injungant quod à ratione &amp; natura plane ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horreat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you ask at laſt, How this Sheet comes out thus alone without the reſt againſt this <hi>Debate</hi> with it? I muſt ſay, What ſhall a man do, when the Preſs is become ſo like the Hedge-hog's Den, that when they have one door open ſtill for themſelves, they will be ſure to ſtop the other, where the leaſt wind can but blow upon them.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:94656:5"/>
            <head>The Animadverſions.</head>
            <p>HAving written out the foregoing ſheet, and left it at the Preſs, there is that Book newly come forth, entituled, <hi>A Diſcourſe of Eccleſiaſtical Polity; wherein the Authority of the Civil Magiſtrate over the Conſcience of Subjects in matters of Religion is aſſerted,</hi> containing eight Chapters, which require this freſh labour.</p>
            <p>The firſt is, <hi>Of the neceſſity of an Eccleſiaſtical Power or Soveraignty over Conſcience;</hi> wherein he ſuppoſing a <hi>competition</hi> between the Power of Princes and the Conſciences of the Subject, gives a ſuperiority to the Power of the Prince above Conſcience. The very Title of this Book, as the flouriſhing ſtile, does ſhew him a young man that writ it. The Conſcience of man is a judgment on his actions in relation to God, that is a judging whether that which he is about to do, is agreeable, or not, to his will: and it is impoſſible that any mortal can have an au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority over that judgment, that the ſubject ſhould do any thing againſt it. That the Commands of the Magiſtrate for the peoples good, do by vertue of the general Inſtitution and fifth Commandment, bind the Conſcience, ſo that if they are bound to the King by the Law of Nature, or Word of God before, this adds a new Obligation; and if they be not, this brings one on them, will be confeſt I think by the moſt judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and ſober in this point: but that the Authority of the Magiſtrate muſt take place of the Authority of Conſcience, when they ſtand in <hi>competition,</hi> is a determination I ſuppoſe that is ſtrange and unheard-of in the Orthodox VVorld. <hi>Every ſingle perſon</hi> (ſayes the Author) <hi>is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to two ſupream powers, the Laws of his Prince, and the Dictates of his Conſcience; and therefore if the ſupream power of the Prince muſt give place to that of the Conſcience, it ceaſes upon that ſcore to be ſupream, becauſe there is a ſuperiour authority that can countermand all its laws and conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi> And who is there that underſtands himſelf, that does not know the ſenſe of this, ſpoken in modeſt and right terms as it ought, is what is moſt true, and what all are to aſſert? The Supremacy of the King, I hope, is over the Subject, as to their Perſons and their Cauſes, not over their Conſciences. If we were to conceive indeed of men that they might chuſe what Conſciences themſelves pleaſed, and then plead them againſt the Magiſtrate, as the face of his words do carry it, that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:94656:5"/>which he ſayes here would have reaſon, and <hi>of all Villains,</hi> the ill-meaning, not the <hi>well-meaning Zealot,</hi> as he ſpeaks, <hi>would be the moſt dangerous.</hi> But when the Conſcience that man hath, is no other then what God hath placed in him, and he hath no power himſelf over it, which is, and muſt, and will be, whether he will or no, concluſive with him according to the Light of Nature, and the Word of God; there is no danger to the Migiſtrate, though ſome of his Commands ſometimes may not actively be obeyed, in yielding that authority which is due, unto Conſcience. And how indeed ſhall a man be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the Magiſtrate for <hi>Conſcience ſake,</hi> if the command of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence had not in it a ſuperiour and more prevalent Power than his? It would be for his own ſake, and not for Conſcience ſake, if his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority were greater than it. I remember, being diſcourſing with ſome about the <hi>Title of this Book,</hi> preſently after I had it, a little Boy, about ten years of age, being carried belike to a Play that week, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing never at one before, had made ſome impreſſions in his mind, <hi>Why Mother,</hi> ſayes he, to her ſtanding by, Lacy <hi>hath confuted this Book; for he acting the Tyrant, ſaid in the Play, That Conſcience was a greater King than he.</hi> I will take this note from hence; It is pity that Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion ſhould be brought as it were on the Stage, and made Comical in the <hi>Friendly Debate;</hi> and that the Stage ſhould ſpeak more truly and tenderly of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> than this Book of <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Polity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Second Chapter is a <hi>more particular account of the Magiſtrates Power in the Affairs of Religion;</hi> the extent whereof he endeavours to ſhew to be the ſame with his power <hi>over the Conſcience in matters of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality.</hi> But this Perſon hath received no long information into his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, I believe, of theſe matters; for he may be pleaſed to know that ſome perhaps of the beſt that have wrote on this ſubject, will grant him freely that the Magiſtrate hath the ſame Power in matters that are <hi>Religious</hi> as in thoſe that are <hi>Moral,</hi> when there is none will ſay that that power is <hi>over the Conſcience</hi> in either. This very daring, as accompliſhed young perſon, too preſuming on his own parts, muſt be acquainted therefore, That it is one thing to grant the King his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in matters Eccleſiaſtical, as well as Civil: and another, to grant him any Authority <hi>over the Conſcience</hi> in the leaſt thing in the world. If the Magiſtrate command any matter of Morality, or of Religion, or of Civil Affairs which are good for the People, that which is comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded does oblige as well in the one, as in the other: But if it be evil which he commands, that is, if it be againſt the Word of God in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, againſt vertue and honeſty in Morals, againſt the common
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:94656:6"/>good in Civils, ſuch things are to be forborn though Commanded; and what, or who can be judge, if it be ſo, but a man's own Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence? And how irrational conſequently, as well as preſumptuous, are ſuch kind of ſpeeches, That <hi>Princes may with leſs hazard give liberty to mens Vices and Debaucheries, than to their Conſciences,</hi> unleſs the acts of men were to be bruitiſh, and performed without judgment?</p>
            <p>His Third Chapter is of the ſubject-matter of the Magiſtrates Power, that is <hi>not the inward acts of the mind, but the outward</hi> actions; from whence he would ſtate the Liberty of the Conſcience to lye al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together in the freedom of a man's thoughts, judgment, or opinion; and that Religious worſhip which is <hi>internal,</hi> when as for his outward actions or practiſes, in the Service of God, as of all things elſe, he would have men <hi>not ſo ſhy of granting the Magiſtrate power</hi> (to uſe ſtill his own language) <hi>over their Conſciences.</hi> But this really is ſhort of what here is to be ſaid, that is a few firſt thoughts taken into the Pen and written away glibly. For though this diſtinction of the <hi>inward</hi> and <hi>outward</hi> acts of men is one thing requiſite to the determining the Point in hand, as you will read in the intended <hi>Diſſertation</hi> following; yet is not that enough alone to ſtate this buſineſs, ſeeing it is about thoſe acts altogether which the Laws and Penalties of the Magiſtrate do reach, we are to make our inquiſition. If this Perſon then (let me ſay) were but able by the ready Tongue and Wit he hath, to prove, That is the outward acts of man only, are ſubject to the Magiſtrate; ſo a man's inward acts only, and heart-worſhip, were ſubject to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience (which he fain methinks would be nibling at) then had he decided the buſineſs very dexterouſly at this one ſtroke, yet not thanks to himſelf for it: But when there is no man, but in his outward acts, and all duty, as in his inward both, is bound, and muſt be (ſay all he can) to follow the dictates of his Conſcience, and that alwayes, ſo far at leaſt as upon no terms whatſoever to go againſt it, the main difficulty of this Determination is quite left untouched by him, and humbly to be aſſayed in that which is to follow.</p>
            <p>His Fourth Chapter is, <hi>Of the Nature of all actions intrinſecally evil, and their exemption from the Authority of humane Laws againſt Mr.</hi> Hobs. When any thing (ſayes he) that is <hi>apparently and intrinſecally evil,</hi> is the matter of an humane Law, whether it be of a Civil or Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Concern, here God is to be obeyed rather than man. And <hi>in all ſuch actions diſobedience is ſo far from being a ſin, that it becomes an in diſpenſable duty.</hi> Thus much is ſaid well, and as others ſay. But when he adds in his <hi>Contents, The reaſon hereof is not becauſe men are
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:94656:6"/>in any thing free from the Supream Authority in Earth, but becauſe they are ſubject to a Superiour in Heaven:</hi> This is ſpoken like a Child, that hath look'd on what he delivers but once, before he delivers it. For the very immediate principal true Reaſon is indeed, becauſe the <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Magiſtrate</hi> and Subordinate, hath no power in ſuch things. Their Authority they have is from God, and that is not to command what he hath forbid, but to be his Miniſters, that is, to rule only for his Glory, and the Peoples Good. This appears by what is ſaid in the firſt ſheet already, and what alſo will follow. And the want of the knowledge of this, hath been a Foundation-ſtone of ſtumbling to many in their deciſions about theſe matters. It follows in the Chapter, that <hi>the taking off all obligations from mens Conſciences antecedent to humane Laws,</hi> does open the way to the <hi>ruine of all Religion,</hi> and conſequently <hi>all Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> This he makes out clearly, and hath well confuted (as I judge) Mr <hi>Hobbs</hi>'s Hypotheſis <hi>of Government.</hi> But in the mean while, I wonder this Author ſhould not ſee, that what he ſayes in the main, does return upon himſelf. For if nothing which is <hi>apparently,</hi> or <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſecally</hi> evil can be commanded by man, becauſe of the Authority of God; then nothing for the ſame reaſon, whatſoever it be which is ſin, or is forbidden at all by Him, can be commanded, ſeeing elſe that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon were not good. As Divines from that ſaying, <hi>We must not do evil that good may come of it,</hi> do unanimouſly agree, that the <hi>leaſt</hi> evil here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon muſt not be committed for the obtaining the <hi>greateſt</hi> good: So will they from the ſaying, <hi>That we muſt obey God rather than man,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude as largely, That whereſoever the Will of God and the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates ſtands in competition, let the matter be <hi>external</hi> or <hi>internal,</hi> intrinſecally or <hi>poſitively</hi> evil, apparently, or an <hi>appearance</hi> only <hi>of evil,</hi> while a man himſelf is convinced in his Conſcience it is evil, it muſt not be done. And what becomes then of the ſubſtance of this Diſcourſe about <hi>the Power of the Magiſtrate over mens Conſciences?</hi> And what a weak Argument, of any in the world, hath he choſen to bottom his main Work upon, which is the ſame Mr <hi>Hobbs,</hi> whom he confutes, I ſuppoſe does bottom his; to wit, an Argument only from <hi>Convenience.</hi> The magiſtrate muſt have a Power over his Subjects Conſciences, becauſe they will elſe be ungovernable, while they obey their own Conſciences rather than him. By which reaſon he might ſay, That therefore his Power in External things, and which concern Goverment, ſhould be above Gods, and the Scriptures; becauſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe the Subject will not obey him when the Word, or God, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires contrary to his Edicts. Certainly, to argue that the People
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:94656:7"/>muſt give the King power over their Conſciences in all things now in difference about Religion, becauſe elſe they cannot be governed by him, is all one as to argue, That when the Prince is wicked, an Atheiſt, an Idolator, an Heathen, the People muſt have no Conſciences at all. That perſon that goes about to looſen the authority of Conſcience with the people, and ſet up a power in any Mortal above that, to rule them by, does but do the ſame thing in a lower degree, as Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> does, and muſt be liable proportionably to the ſame Conſequences. And is it not pity when a man is ſo ſtoutly confuting Mr. <hi>Hobbs,</hi> that he in the mean while ſhould become a young <hi>Leviathan</hi> himſelf, who gives the world occaſion too, to fear what he may grow to? But whatſoever dimenſions he may have as to his parts, his ſtrength hitherto is but little. Thoſe Subjects that will but heartily obey their Prince ſo much as they can, that is, ſo far as their Conſciences will let them, they obey him enough; and are as governable as God Almighty would have them. If this man would have more, he does but find fault with his <hi>Maker,</hi> and with humane Nature, as if he did not know how beſt to make man fit for Government; which is for none but one of the light young men, and fooliſh of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to do. As <hi>incommodum non ſoluit,</hi> I aſſume, <hi>Ex commodo, non valet Argumentum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His fifth Chapter is concerning <hi>Toleration,</hi> as it ariſes from Atheiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Principles. Thoſe that are indifferent in their Religion, or have no Religion, cannot be concerned much with what others hold. It is againſt reaſon, and a kind of madneſs, that ſuch ſhould be vehement for perſecution. There are Arguments therefore which are uſed by this ſort of men, from Policy for Liberty of all Opinions, which this perſon endeavours to prevent or remove, and does offer ſome of his own againſt Toleration. But this Subject hath been lately ſo much canvaſed, and there are arguments drawn up ſo fully and clearly, with ſo much weight and prudence, from the Intereſt of Religion, and from the Intereſt of our State, in thoſe two Books or two parts, entituled, <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> and the laſt eſpecially, that it will ſcarcely admit of any thing more to be ſaid of it: If it will, it is the fixing a right ſtate hereof onely in the Mind, that will be, I think, both the beſt way to confirm it, and to preponderate the Arguments againſt it. It pleaſed his Majeſty in one of his Speeches to commend a Union of his Proteſtant Subjects to the conſideration of the Parliament: A Deſign full of all Princely Wiſdom, Honeſty, and Goodneſs: In this Atchiev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, there is a double Intereſt (I apprehend) to be diſtinguiſhed and conſidered; That of Religion it ſelf, and that of the Nation. The
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:94656:7"/>advance of Religion does conſiſt much in the Unity of its Profeſſors, both in Opinion and Practice, to be of one Mind, and one Heart, and one way (in Diſcipline and Worſhip, if it might be) according to the the Scripture. The advance of the Nation does lie in the freedom and flouriſhing of Trade, and uniting the whole Body in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon benefit and dependance on the Government. The one of theſe beſpeaks an <hi>Eſtabliſhed Order</hi> or <hi>Accommodation,</hi> the other beſpeaks <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence, Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> or <hi>Toleration.</hi> For while People are in danger about Religion, we dare not launch out into Trade (ſay they) but muſt keep our Money, ſeeing we know not what we ſhall ſuffer, nor where we ſhall be driven. And when in reference to their Party or Parties, they are held under ſeverity, it is eaſie for thoſe who are deſigning Heads, to mould them into Wrath and Faction; which with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out that Rigor ſhall melt and reſolve into bare Diſſent onely in Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, peaceably rejoycing under the enjoyment of Protection. The King we know is concerned as the <hi>Supreme</hi> Governour, and as a <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> Proteſtant Governour. As he is <hi>King,</hi> he is to ſeek the welfare of the Nation; as he is <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> the flouriſhing of Religion: And the Proteſtant Religion particularly is his Intereſt, as this Kingdom does lie in balance (He being the chief Party) with its Neighbour Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations. The Judgement now of ſome is for a <hi>Comprehending</hi> Act, which may take in thoſe who will own the National Church, that ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity then might be uſed for reclaiming all whoſoever ſeparate from it. The Judgement of ſome others is, For a free and equal Act of Grace to all indifferently, (the Papiſts with ſome, excepted) whether Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts or others; abhorring Comprehenſion as more dangerous to them upon the Account mentioned, than all the Acts that yet have paſſed. Neither of theſe judge up to the full Intereſt of the King and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, as is propoſed. It becomes not the <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> if his Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples will admit him to own our Pariſh Churches, and enjoy a Living, to be willing to have his Brethren the <hi>Independent</hi> given up to perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: And it becomes not the Separatiſt if he may but enjoy his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, to repine or envy at the Presbyterian for reaping any farther Emolument, ſeeing both of them (ſuppoſing the latter may do ſo) have as much at the bottom as can be, in their Capacities, deſired of either. It is an Act therefore of a <hi>mixt</hi> complexion, providing both <hi>Compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion,</hi> and <hi>Indulgence</hi> for the different Parties, muſt ſerve our purpoſe. Let but the Grounds for Comprehenſion be laid wide enough, to take in all who can own, and come to the publick Church and Miniſtry, which we ſuppoſe as yet the far greater weight of the Nation, and when
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:94656:8"/>the Countenance of the King, or State-Emoluments are all caſt into one Scale, and others let alone to come of it, without perſecuting any to inflame them, or Preferment to encourage them, (eſpecially if one expedient were added, that is, if the Deans and Chapters Lands, and all Pluralities impartially, the one whereof are held unprofitably, the other ſinfully, were caſt into the Labouring Miniſtry, that thoſe that come in, may find it really better to be a <hi>Prieſt</hi> to a Tribe, than a <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite</hi> onely to a Family) we need not doubt but Time, the Miſtreſs of the Wiſe and the Unwiſe, would diſcover the peaceable iſſue of ſuch Counſels.</p>
            <p>His Sixth Chapter is, <hi>Of indifferent things, and the Magistrates power in determining them;</hi> wherein that Tenet, <hi>That nothing ought to be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed in the Worſhip of God, either in matter or manner, but what is commanded in Gods Word,</hi> is exagitated and burdened with ſeveral evil Conſequences. But this Author is not to go away with this wrong, to lay that for a Principle of Nonconformity, which the moſt ſober of the Nonconformiſts will diſclaim. This Poſition therefore, <hi>That no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is lawful in Gods Worſhip, but what he hath enjoyned,</hi> muſt be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of the Worſhip of God as to the <hi>Subſtance</hi> of it; wherein it is true, That what is not commanded is <hi>co nomine</hi> forbidden. But as for the <hi>Circumſtances</hi> of it, it muſt admit of ſome diſtinction, upon neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, and if we go to frame any, as of <hi>natural</hi> Circumſtances and <hi>inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute,</hi> or the like, unleſs the diſtinction be derived from Scripture, that which we aſſume of the one branch, will go near by a parity of Reaſon, to be ſtretched alſo to the other. The determination then of my thoughts, is this. There is the <hi>Worſhip</hi> of God, and the <hi>Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances</hi> of it. The Worſhip of God muſt be what he hath preſcribed; if it be not commanded by him, it is not our Duty, and ſo cannot be his Worſhip. The Circumſtances of his Worſhip I account are either neceſſary, or not: By neceſſary, I will underſtand neceſſary to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined: If they be neceſſary, and he hath not preſcribed them, our Superiours may enjoyn them, and we are to obey them. If they be not neceſſary, I queſtion whether the Church hath authority to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn them; or if it hath, a <hi>need-not,</hi> is a reaſon why ſhe ſhould not; and it is beſt however to me beyond doubt, ſhe ſhould rather let them alone: <hi>It ſeemeth good to us and the holy Ghoſt, to lay upon you no greater burden than theſe neceſſary things.</hi> If yet nevertheleſs the Church for her part (or our Superiours) will impoſe things that are unneceſſary, and they do but ill in it, I do apprehend that we for our part notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding have that advantage by our Liberty as Chriſtians, that ſo long
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:94656:8"/>as the thing is not againſt our Conſciences, nor will cauſe our Brother to ſin, we may and ſhall do well to obey them for quietneſs, and the Magiſtrates ſake. I will yet proceed. When ſome underſtanding perſons have ſaid, <hi>That things which were indifferent before, may become unlawful being enjoyned:</hi> We muſt carefully diſtinguiſh between a thing being <hi>commanded as neceſſary,</hi> and being <hi>neceſſary as commanded.</hi> It is true, that when a thing indifferent is commanded as neceſſary, (as a part of Worſhip, or as if God requir'd the ſame of us) it becomes unlawful, or rather it is to be refuſed and not done, becauſe comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded as ſuch. Jeſus Chriſt would not obſerve the Traditions of the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders (I humbly conceive) upon this account, becauſe they held them neceſſary, uſing them as if there were ſome holineſs in them, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed as equal with the Precept of God, if not above it, when they made it become void thereby; or elſe he might have done is they did, in many of them. And hence <hi>Paul</hi> withſtood <hi>Peter,</hi> as I judge: The Jews by his Fact were like to think the obſervation of <hi>Moſes</hi> Law in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpenſible; when otherwiſe he made nothing of circumciſing <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy,</hi> and doing himſelf according to it. To this purpoſe are we to <hi>ſtand faſt in our Liberty,</hi> and not to be the Servants of Men. But if a thing be held neceſſary onely as commanded, we are to diſtinguiſh of that <hi>neceſſity,</hi> and of thoſe <hi>things.</hi> Things that are commanded (we ſuppoſe them to concern Religion) are either for <hi>Edification,</hi> or <hi>not:</hi> And this neceſſity is either in regard of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> or the <hi>outward Man.</hi> If things commanded be for Edification (or if we are convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced they are ſo) then is there truly a neceſſity in regard of Conſcience, or an obligation on the Conſcience to obey them, as authorized from God. If they are not tending to edifie, (or we in our Conſciences ſo judge in ſincerity) then are they to be look'd on as not neceſſary in point of Conſcience; becauſe the authority that the Superiour hath in ſuch things, is onely for Edification; <hi>According to the Power given us of God for Edification:</hi> And conſequently, they being not (I ſay) <hi>edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> things, thoſe particular Commands have none of Gods Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty (as I have ſaid in my firſt ſheet, on another occaſion before; where what is wanting here, may be ſupplied) and cannot be obligatory in Conſcience, ſo as to be ſaid, upon that account, neceſſary to be done. Nevertheleſs there is a neceſſity in regard of the Outward Man, that remains, which is, that rather than reſiſt the Magiſtrate, we muſt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer; and rather than ſuffer, we are forced to chuſe to do the thing. And herein then are we I account beholding to that Liberty that the Lord Jeſus Chriſt hath purchaſed, that we may obey in indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:94656:9"/>things, and are not put upon the neceſſity of ſuffering altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>His Seventh Chapter is, <hi>of the nature and obligation of Scandal, and the abſurdity</hi> (as he ſpeaks) <hi>of pretending it againſt the Commands of Authority;</hi> wherein there are ſeveral things according to the fluent ability of the Author; among which, there is not wanting <hi>that</hi> perhaps which ſhould be ſaid; but there is wanting a ſenſible judgement of the Caſe it ſelf, unto which, what he ſayes ſhould be applied. For not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all this he hath here about Scandal, I do not find that really he yet knows (or at leaſt but at adventure) what that Scandal is, or wherein the Point of it lyes that pierceth the Conſcientious in the buſineſs of Conformity, that when there are ſome things which ſome of them otherwiſe might do as lawful, according to their own Conſciences, they dare not but for bear them for the Conſcience ſake of others. <hi>Conſcience I ſay, not thy own, but of the others.</hi> I will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire this Perſon to read, or to read better, that little Tract of Scandal writ by Dr. <hi>Hammond,</hi> who will ſhew him, wherein the Apoſtle to the <hi>Romans</hi> and to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> does place the matter of Scandal, and the reſult will come to this, That no man upon any terms may e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver do that thing whereof he is ſatisfied himſelf of the lawfulneſs of it, ſo long as he hath reaſon to be perſwaded that by his example he ſhall induce others to do the ſame, who being unſatisfied in their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences about it, ſhall ſin in the doing. And <hi>if he ſin againſt the Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and wound their weak Conſciences, he ſins againſt Christ.</hi> This is the Caſe of Scandal with the <hi>Nonconformist.</hi> A man may not ſin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Chriſt for the Magiſtrates command. But for ſome men to Conform, will be to do thus: <hi>Ergo.</hi> By this little may appear the inſufficiency and impertinency of thoſe things which this man and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, do commoly offer for ſatisfaction in the caſe of Scandal. <hi>The matters wherein Scandal is concern'd</hi> (ſays he) <hi>are only indifferent things, but nothing that is not antecedently ſinful remains ſo, after the commands of Authority.</hi> This expreſſion ſure can hardly hold ſenſe; but as for the meaning, I Anſwer. The doing the leaſt indifferent matter in any particular whatſoever, which is Scandal in the Apoſtles ſenſe, is <hi>antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently evil,</hi> and conſequently this great Anſwer comes to nothing. Again, <hi>We encounter Scandal with Scandal;</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>The complying with Authority, offends only the weak Brethren, or a few of them; but the refuſing offends the whole Church and Magiſtrate.</hi> I Anſwer, The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing, is not doing that which the Apoſtle means, when he gives us ſuch a charge about Scandal, according to Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi>'s true inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:94656:9"/>thereof in that Tract; nor what Chriſt means when he ſpeaks ſo dreadfully of <hi>offending any of his little Ones</hi> in the Goſpel. Conſequently this Anſwer comes to nothing likewiſe. I will add, It is better that a man offend the whole world with that offence which conſiſts only in <hi>diſpleaſure,</hi> then to offend any one the leaſt Chriſtian in that ſenſe wherein the Apoſtle and Chriſt forbids Scandal. I know I have not framed my words here in ſuch a ſtyle as to make them pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent; but I have ſpoken to the matter, which I chuſe rather.</p>
            <p>His Laſt Chapter is, <hi>of a tender, doubtful, and unſatisfied Conſcience;</hi> wherein he endeavours to prove by that <hi>one</hi> Topick ſtill, from <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience</hi> and <hi>inconvenience,</hi> and then to perſwade us hereupon, That in <hi>all doubtful and diſputable Caſes, we ſhould take the Commands of Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity for the Supreme Rule of Conſcience;</hi> and that <hi>to act against our own Scruples out of obedience</hi> thereunto, is godlineſs and <hi>vertue.</hi> A ſtrange Chapter! There is nothing hardly more manifeſt and uncontroulable in Practical Divinity, than that a Chriſtian may not do any thing with a Conſcience unſatisfied of the lawfulneſs of what he does, but that he is firſt to be perſwaded thereof in his mind before he does it. The Scripture is moſt expreſs for this. That in things indifferent, he that <hi>eſteems them unclean,</hi> to him they are unclean. He that <hi>acts not in Faith,</hi> that is with a perſwaſion, that the thing he does is lawful, and will not diſpleaſe God, <hi>does ſin.</hi> And he that <hi>eateth and doubteth, is damned if he eat.</hi> I wonder therefore with what heart this Perſon here can uſe his Parts and Oratory in this Argument, which is to prevail on People that by all means they would be contented, and not be ſo ſhy, or make any ſuch matter as they are apt to do of it, to be <hi>damned.</hi> To do any thing againſt a mans Conſcience how indifferent ſoever, is to do that, in the doing whereof a man is <hi>damned,</hi> that is, does commit a deadly ſin. But if I make the Command of Authority my ſupream Rule in indifferent things, when Authority commands any thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt my Conſcience, I muſt act againſt my Conſcience in that thing. Conſequently this Author hath beſtowed this Chapter to perſwade men to damnation. I muſt confeſs the Man hath ſuch a pretty glib and voluble expreſſion, that if he will ſpeak friendly of any known ſin, or ſmoothly of Hell, he may prevail no doubt with many to ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture on both, who really believe them nothing: But if any indeed do believe his Religion true, and contained in theſe Scriptures, I muſt adviſe him for his life, not to hearken to this young man's counſel, but that fixing that old and good rule, <hi>Quod dubitas ne feceris,</hi> in his mind, he reſolve to look well to the virginity of his Conſcience, leſt in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:94656:10"/>once what he <hi>fears</hi> to be unlawful, he comes afterwards to proſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute it to any thing he <hi>knows</hi> to be ſo. The truth is, the ſum of this Chapter is very raſh and prophane, That <hi>whatſoever be our own judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and apprehenſions, we must acquieſce in the determinations</hi> of our Governors. <hi>And every Conſcience that is not thus perſwaded, is to be reskoned as ſeditious and unpeaceable, and ſo to be treated accordingly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I purpoſe not to enter further into Examination of the <hi>particulars</hi> of theſe Chapters, which may be done more eaſily in good time, by me or others. There are <hi>three</hi> or <hi>four things</hi> remarkable to me upon the <hi>whole Diſcourſe.</hi> The <hi>first</hi> is the Magnificence of the Author's Pen and trouling Expreſſion, and indeed excellent Parts. The <hi>next</hi> is the very fine Paper and Print of the Book. This I ſet down becauſe as to the matter it ſelf, theſe <hi>two things,</hi> the fine Expreſſion and the fine Paper, are but indeed regardable alike. The <hi>third</hi> is the Scorn, Preſumption, and Pride (wherein the man muſt be acknowledg'd un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parallel'd) with which it is writ. And the <hi>last</hi> is, the ſhortneſs and unſatisfactorineſs in the iſſue. For when he tells us at the end, that he hath been <hi>ſollicitous not to baulk any thing material,</hi> but hath <hi>encountred</hi> all the <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> moſt <hi>weighty and conſiderable</hi> Objections, he hath not truly once touched thoſe things in good earneſt, which are the preſent certain grounds of <hi>Nonconformity</hi> and <hi>Separation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are two ſorts we know of Diſſenters from the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Thoſe that are of the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> judgment, and are for accommodation with her: And thoſe that are of the <hi>Congregational</hi> judgment, who ſeparate from her, and cannot own any but their ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered Churches.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>Congregationalists,</hi> they ſtand here: The Church of Chriſt is a number of the truly faithful, and regenerate Perſons. The viſible Church is defined by a profeſſion of true Regenerate Faith, and of no leſs than that, according to the general opinion of the <hi>Proteſtant Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines.</hi> In our <hi>Pariſh Churches</hi> now they alleage, there is no Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion made of true Grace by any unto Memberſhip, at leaſt not ſuch as is credible, and no watching over one another after, as Brethren in fellowſhip. And conſequently there is no viſible Church amongſt us. As for Profeſſion of Infants at their Baptiſm, that is as good as nothing to them, ſeeing Profeſſion is a thing not to be required for it ſelf; but for the ſignifying to the Church or Miniſter, what the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is who makes the Profeſſion, that accordingly he may admit or not admit them to Church-Communion. And as for <hi>Confirmation,</hi> we know it is not ſo uſed, nor can any prove it to be inſtituted to that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:94656:10"/>uſe in the Goſpel. It follows, that our <hi>National</hi> or <hi>Pariſh Churches</hi> being not companies of <hi>Profeſſors,</hi> they muſt gather their Churches that are ſuch; and here lies the true ground of <hi>Separation.</hi> And does this Perſon yet know this? Or hath he ſpoken a word of it? Or dare he take this file into his mouth, but it will wear out his teeth? Let me ſee what he, and his whole Party, laying their wits together, will be able to ſay in this Point to purpoſe. But let not any one do it rawly, without conſidering the weight which is here included. For if there is nothing to be ſaid by him, but that all the Members of our Pariſhes are indeed ſuch Profeſſors, that is, a number as have, or do ſo credibly profeſs their Faith, Repentance, Regeneration, and the ſaving Grace of God, that the Miniſter hath, or doth thereupon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them as a People endowed all with this Grace, ſuppoſed to be profeſſed; and that the <hi>viſible Church</hi> muſt be granted indeed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and the <hi>Book</hi> of our <hi>Liturgy,</hi> to be a number of ſuch, and no leſs Profeſſors than ſuch, I doubt me they will prevail little more with the <hi>Nonconformist</hi> of this <hi>make,</hi> than to root them in their Practiſe; and to judge that <hi>Separation</hi> is indeed from this Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple a moſt apparent reſult, and undeniably concluded. What man is there alive of ſuch parts, as dares revive Mr. <hi>Blake's</hi> Cauſe, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend it againſt Mr. <hi>Baxter's Right to Sacraments?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> or thoſe <hi>Nonconformiſts,</hi> who are for Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and go under that Name, there are many for ought I ſee, not concern'd in any objection throughout this Book, unleſs, it be in that of Scandal, and ſome are not concern'd in that; for it is not thoſe that are <hi>peeviſh,</hi> as this man thinks, or will be angry at one, and endure him no more if he <hi>conform,</hi> that a man need trouble himſelf about ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalizing, The obeying the Magiſtrate is more than that: but it is thoſe <hi>tender conſcienced</hi> and <hi>humble good natured</hi> Perſons, that love a man and eſteem him, and ſo are like to do as he does only for his example (and thereby may wound their <hi>Conſciences</hi> as the matter is ſhewn before) that a man is to be ſo <hi>cautious of in the caſe of Scandal.</hi> I ſay, there are <hi>many</hi> who refuſe not happily to <hi>Conform to the Liturgy,</hi> nor any of <hi>their things</hi> indifferent (which they wiſh yet rather <hi>chang'd</hi> or <hi>forborn</hi>) but they refuſe to <hi>conform</hi> to <hi>Lying</hi> and <hi>Perjury;</hi> That is, they refuſe to <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare and Subſcribe</hi> according to the <hi>Act of Uniformity,</hi> and to take the <hi>Oxford Oath.</hi> And who does not know what <hi>Act</hi> that was that <hi>made</hi> ſuch <hi>Nonconformiſts?</hi> What is the reaſon then that this <hi>Undertaker</hi> hath ſaid nothing in <hi>defence</hi> of theſe <hi>new Impoſitions,</hi> and the <hi>Subſcription</hi> in the <hi>Canons?</hi> If he can Anſwer what is <hi>objected againſt them,</hi> and the <hi>Oxford
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:94656:11"/>Oath,</hi> in the Book mentioned in the <hi>firſt Sheet,</hi> we ſhall thank him: if he cannot, To what purpoſe does he beat the air about <hi>Conformity,</hi> till there be ſome <hi>condeſcention</hi> in ſuch things, as the <hi>truly conſcientious</hi> may be preſſed to <hi>obey,</hi> with the face of <hi>ingenuity</hi> and <hi>righteouſneſs?</hi> As for this Book we have here already, we ſee it carried on againſt <hi>theſe men,</hi> as if <hi>they</hi> were ſo many <hi>villains,</hi> that in all their Arguments ſought <hi>pretences</hi> only for their <hi>Nonconformity:</hi> and when the great <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage</hi> they get by it, is only to be <hi>Ejected</hi> from their <hi>Livings</hi> and <hi>loſe</hi> what they <hi>had,</hi> and out of real <hi>conviction</hi> of the unlawfulneſs of theſe <hi>Declarations</hi> and <hi>Subſcriptions</hi> that are <hi>impoſed</hi> upon them, they forbear them and are quiet; This man comes with his <hi>other things,</hi> and concludes upon them, <hi>And what inſtance have we in any Nation of the World, of any Schiſm and Faction ſo unreaſonably begun and continued! The Rebellion of</hi> Corah <hi>indeed may reſemble, but nothing can equal it.</hi> By which, and ſuch-like Expreſſions as theſe, the <hi>Author,</hi> I doubt me, will hardly prove himſelf, <hi>a Perſon of</hi> ſuch <hi>a tame and ſoftly hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour</hi> as he <hi>aſſures</hi> us: Nor may he, perhaps, when he hath reflected well on the <hi>deſign</hi> and <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of what he hath wrote, which is really but an open tendring that Scandal to his Brethren (in his ſort) which Chriſt and his Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul</hi> hath ſo forewarned us <hi>to take heed of</hi> (which is the inducing the Tender and Conſcientious to do thoſe things whereof they are unſatisfied, and ſo to ſin in the doing) have ſo much confidence as he now ſeems to have, in what he has done. For if <hi>the black Ox</hi> ſhall come to <hi>tread</hi> once on this young man's <hi>foot,</hi> and he grow graver; or if it ſhall pleaſe the Lord to touch his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous ſoul with the ſenſe and horror of that one text, or ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, That it were better that <hi>a Milſtone were hung about his neck and he thrown into the Sea, then that one of Chriſt's little ones,</hi> who are now tender of their Conſciences, ſhould do what he hath adviſed; it may be, I ſay, the poor man may have reaſon to change his Concluſion, to pray to Gods above all men, that his Book take no effect; and taking little joy what <hi>Pilate</hi> did, to with-draw the breath of his Defiance, and to wiſh, that <hi>What he hath written,</hi> were <hi>unwritten.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reader,</hi> there is an Anſwer come freſh out to the <hi>Friendly Debate,</hi> which is yet wholly unſeen to me. There is alſo a little Book of a ſubject very rarely before offered to the Publick, entituled, <hi>The Childrens-Petition and Remonſtrance to the Parliament,</hi> preſented belike to both Houſes on Wedneſday laſt; which appears to me of ſuch concern to poſterity, that I cannot but take this ſpare place be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween theſe Papers to give notice of it, as fit to be furthered upon that account by all who are lovers of Purity and ingenuous Virtue.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:94656:11"/>
            <head>The Diſſertation.</head>
            <p>THe Diſcourſe of <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Polity</hi> came to my hand within two or three days after it came abroad; I kept it by me about juſt a week, and then carried the preceding <hi>Animadverſions</hi> to the Preſs, to come out with the firſt ſheet: But how many weeks it may be ere they be printed, I know not: In the mean while, I think good to prepare two or three more, in regard of one ſubject, which is ſo neceſſary to be adjoyned, that it lies at the bottom of all our buſineſs. That is, Concerning the Power of the <hi>Civil</hi> Magiſtrate, in <hi>Religious</hi> Affairs. I muſt confeſs I have ſome Papers by me, beſides thoſe againſt the <hi>Friendly Debate,</hi> which are not controverſal and contentious; but heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and tending to peace: The Original Deſign whereof, was, for Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration on both ſides; to wit, For Condeſcention on the part of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority towards Tender Conſciences, and for ſubmiſſion on the part of the Subject, (ſo far as every one can) to what is eſtabliſhed. I ſhall leave thoſe Papers perhaps but the more entire in their proper matter, and yet ſupply my ſelf here out of ſome former years thoughts for this preſent occaſion.</p>
            <p>Indeed the power of the Supreme Magiſtrate in things Religious, is a buſineſs of great Concern, and aſſured Difficulty. That the Church is to be govern'd by thoſe Officers whom God hath ſet in it, appears reaſonable. That ſuch are Apoſtles, Paſtors and Teachers, unto whom the Keys are committed and not the Sword, cannot be denied. That when there is no <hi>formal</hi> power then at all in the Magiſtrate over the Church of Chriſt, there is ſome Superintendent inſpection neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs belonging to him, as <hi>Epiſcopus</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in Eccleſiaſtical Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, the Example of the good Kings in the Old Teſtament, and <hi>Conſtantine</hi> under the times of the New, and the Confeſſions of all Churches, will allow. That in the exerciſe of this external <hi>objective</hi> power, which he hath in the Church, he is not to be a blind Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor onely of the Biſhops will, in putting a Sanction on their Canons, and enforcing the obſervance, without having the <hi>Book of the Law de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to him,</hi> and conſequently a Judgement of Diſcretion, whether they be agreeable to the Rule of Gods Word, and condition of his People, the conſonant Judgement of Proteſtants will aſſert on all
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:94656:12"/>hands. Now then when the Magiſtrate hath <hi>ſomething to do,</hi> and not <hi>all to do</hi> in theſe Affairs, how, or how far this Authority of his, is to be maintained or ſtated, that it intrench not on the <hi>Liberty of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> which is due to his Chriſtian Subjects, (as peculiar and ſacred to God) is the Attempt, I perceive, of ſome late Papers bearing that Title; The Arguments whereof (eſpecially as to the Nations Intereſt) I have already praiſed: The ſtate of the Queſtion I judge alſo, to be tendered with much Ingenuity and Reaſon; but when they come to the very point where I expect their notion fixt, that I might ſet my foot upon it, and ſtand faſt, I find the ground methinks ſinking away from its Foundation.</p>
            <p>Let us conſult Common Places on that head <hi>De Magistrata,</hi> and we ſhall find theſe are made two Queſtions by Divines: <hi>Whether the Magistrate is to TAKE CARE of Religion? Whether he is to COM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PEL HIS S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BJECTS to it?</hi> And when the former is granted gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally from that Text, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17, 18. and that Tenet, That he is <hi>Custos utrinſque Tabutae;</hi> the latter is denied, yet with Caution. Diſtinguiſh (ſay they) between <hi>Cogere ad fidem,</hi> and <hi>i<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>terdicere exercitio in hetero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxia. Poſterius ad evitandum corruptionem &amp; ſcandala competit Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratui.</hi> Diſtinguiſh again of a Commonwealth or Kingdom, free or not free from divers Religions. <hi>Ibi cavendae, hic tolerandae, ſed cum conditione ne publica Religionis exercitia heterodoxis facile concedantur:</hi> By this little, we ſee a door open for Chriſtian Prudence to be let in to the deciſion of theſe matters, which being guided by the Light of Univerſal Nature, and the General Rules of Scripture, muſt needs make very much way for variety of Judgement and Practiſe in the Caſe.</p>
            <p>To ſtate theſe matters then a little, which our purpoſe requires.</p>
            <p>The Civil Magiſtrate (ſays the Apoſtle) <hi>is the Miniſter of God for our good:</hi> The Souls good is the beſt good. <hi>Ea eſt optima Reſpublica,</hi> with <hi>Ariſtotle; Ex cujus inſtituto quiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> optimè &amp; beatiſſime vivat.</hi> As Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion makes Folks be<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Subjects, and beſt men, it makes them moſt happy, having <hi>the Promiſes of this Life,</hi> with a better. The inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Magiſtrate upon this Account appears to be for this End, That the People may <hi>lead peaceable Lives</hi> under him, in all <hi>Godlineſs</hi> as well as <hi>Honesty.</hi> It is not conſequently for us here to imagine, that the Magiſtrates Authority does extend onely to Civil Things, but to take a care of Sacred alſo, and to ſee the Will of God to be executed in both. <hi>Im<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>atores ſacra &amp; ſaecularia ex aequo curant; ſin ad ſingula veniatur, fatendum eſt anguſtius eſſe jus imperii circa ſacra quam circa
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:94656:12"/>profana, bac una ratione, quod Lex divina de ſacris plura conſtituat, &amp; libertati eximat, quam de caeteris rebus.</hi> To this purpoſe we muſt know that Actions or Things, <hi>quae ſubjacont humano imperio,</hi> are either ſuch as are determined and neceſſary, being commanded or forbidden of God; or ſuch as are indifferent, being left undetermined by him. In Things or Actions which God hath forbidden or commanded, that is, which he hath <hi>determined,</hi> to wit, either by the Law of Nature, or Divine poſitive Inſtitution, the <hi>Duty</hi> of the Magiſtrate does lie in removing Obſtacles, adminiſtring Helps, and withdrawing Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the ſin; but his <hi>Power</hi> preciſely does lie in ſuper-adding a new Obligation to that of Gods, and by the ſanction and infliction of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, to inforce unto the Duty. And ſo is he a <hi>Keeper</hi> onely of the two <hi>Tables,</hi> having no Right of changing a Tittle of Gods Will. In things left indifferent, and not determined by God, that is, in things which are neither written in the mind of Man, nor Gods Word, <hi>Haec ſive ſacra, ſivè profana ſint, determinare in alteram partem Jus eſt ſummae poteſtatis;</hi> The Magiſtrate hath <hi>Power</hi> here, and <hi>Liberty;</hi> Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to determine, and Power thereby to change ſuch things into lawful and unlawful, according as he requires or prohibits them for the ſpiritual or temporal good of his people; and the effects of that Command or Prohibition, are Obligation and Coercion.</p>
            <p>This premiſed, the ingenuous Papers before mentioned, after they have endeavoured to ſhew the extremity of three Opinions about the Magiſtrates power in Religions Things; In ſome that make him the ſole Judge of all Matters Spiritual and Temporal; In others, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm the like power, but to be exerciſed in Spirituals, in a perfect ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerviency to the Church; In a third, that make him have nothing to do but in Civil Matters onely, (wherein, if that Truth rather, which lies contained in thoſe extream Opinions, as <hi>omne falſum in nititur vero,</hi> ſhould be diſcovered, (inſtead of their bare rejection) and laid well together, the moſt mature account of the Magiſtrate, in reference to this point, were I think to be given) they bring the whole to this iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue, <hi>That the Magistrate is the great Office<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Minister</hi> (as the Apoſtle calls him) <hi>of God upon Earth, to ſee his Will</hi> (which in Religion they count (if I miſapprehend them not) is what alone he hath revealed) <hi>to be put in execution.</hi> And then for the reſcuing that liberty they would aſſert and keep for the Conſcience, they put in, <hi>That under the Goſpel the Magiſtrate muſt do this in the manner alſo that Chriſt hath appointed, and ſo not by the temporal Sword.</hi> This is to profeſs a great matter and momentous Truth, but in the fulneſs of the Authors own pious and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:94656:13"/>weighty Conceptions, he hath left his <hi>Reader</hi> at a perfect loſs of the true account, when we are brought as it were too, almoſt within ken of it. I muſt humbly crave pardon therefore, if I bring a few of my dryer thoughts here, to miniſter to his abundance.</p>
            <p>The Office it ſelf of the Magiſtrate is to bear the Sword, and by that to act, or effect what it his to do. Where a Perſon hath no power of <hi>Coercion,</hi> he acts not as a Magiſtrate, but as another man, as an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent Member only of the Society; and he that ſayes, He may not uſe the <hi>temporal Sword in the concerns of the Goſpel,</hi> does upon the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſay, That <hi>quâ Magiſtrate,</hi> he hath <hi>nothing to do at all</hi> in Religion, which is an acknowledged Errour. What the Will of God then is, we are orderly to enquire here, which the Magiſtrate is to ſee done. It is the Will of God that People ſhould be Converted, that they ſhould Believe, Repent, and be ſaved: And it is his Will that the Goſpel be preached, and his Ordinances attended to that end. It is not to be thought, I ſuppoſe, the Office of the Magiſtrate concerns both theſe alike without diſtinction. If men are not converted, and believe not, he cannot make them do that. But if the Miniſter neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lects his duty of Preaching, Catechiſing, Adminiſtring the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or Cenſures which Chriſt commands in order thereunto, the Magiſtrate may puniſh him, becauſe herein he hath power, when he cannot adminiſter the Ordinances and Excommunicate any himſelf, wherein he hath none committed to him, <hi>Aliud enins eſt imperium circa ſacra, aliud ſacra functio.</hi> If the People likewiſe be looſe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, and upon that account come not to Church but neglect God, he may puniſh them for their not coming, which, I hope, is in the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns of the Goſpel,</hi> although if they abſtain only upon doubt, ſcruple, or reaſon of Conſcience, there is difference in the matter. There are therefore the <hi>inward</hi> or the <hi>outward</hi> acts of men. When the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate is ſaid to be <hi>the Miniſter of God,</hi> and conſequently to ſee his Will performed, it muſt be underſtood, not ſimply and indefinitely, but <hi>reſtrictè, &amp; ſecundum quid,</hi> in reference to mens <hi>outward</hi> acts, and the <hi>inward</hi> as they are concern'd only in the <hi>outward.</hi> Neither muſt we confound the diſtinctions of <hi>ſacred</hi> and <hi>civil</hi> actions with <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> and <hi>outward</hi> in this place. The power of the Magiſtrate may extend to <hi>both</hi> in the <hi>one,</hi> but does not in the <hi>other.</hi> The inward acts of men are not within his Cognizance, and ſo not under his Juriſdiction. The Government of the Church accordingly is <hi>internal,</hi> and <hi>external.</hi> The <hi>internal</hi> government of it belongs to Chriſt; It is he alone can rule mens hearts. The Magiſtrate can but look to the <hi>outward</hi> acts;
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:94656:13"/>and <hi>his kingdom</hi> is, when Chriſt's <hi>is not, of this world.</hi> This external rule again of the Church, or Church-affairs, muſt be diſtinguiſhed into <hi>two ſorts;</hi> It is <hi>one ſort</hi> belongs to the <hi>Paſtor</hi> and Church-guides; and <hi>another</hi> to the <hi>Magiſtrate.</hi> For inſtance, the Magiſtrate cannot be ſaid properly to make Cinons (ſayes <hi>Bramhal</hi> of Schiſm) being preſcribed under pain of Excommunication, and yet can they have no obligation (<hi>Grotius</hi> ſhews) on the Subjects, but by <hi>Empire</hi> only. The <hi>one</hi> is then<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Eccleſia regimen externum formale;</hi> the <hi>other, Externum ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectivum.</hi> The <hi>one</hi> is, <hi>directive, ſwaſory, declarative;</hi> The <hi>other, Juris conſtitutivum, imperatory, coercive.</hi> This I take to be certain, that into whatſoever the <hi>Rule</hi> of the Magiſtrate extends, his <hi>Sword</hi> muſt. What he may <hi>command,</hi> he may <hi>compel;</hi> that is, he may puniſh if the command be not fulfilled; and where he cannot <hi>compel,</hi> he cannot <hi>command.</hi> I ſpeak as to the ſtanding Power, not the Exerciſe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in prudence is to direct. It is true, the pious Magiſtrate is to deſire and endeavour the ſalvation of his People; He is to ſeek their good, and the ſpiritual good is beyond their temporal. But he is to do this (I hope) in his ſphere, according to his place, as far only as he can, that is, as far as his Sword will go. His Sword will not reach the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man: If it would, he might, he ſhould uſe it no doubt to do them good. But ſeeing it will not, he is to ſee then that the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Sword be applied, the Word preached, and the Miniſters office executed; and how is he to ſee to that, to cauſe, on enforce that, and the People to attend thereunto, but by the authority of his Sword? To ſay or think then becauſe the Salvation of mens Souls is wrought by God's grace, not by outward force; that is, becauſe the Goſpel is the power of God to that end, and the Weapons are ſpiritual, not car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, that is able to do this; Therefore the Magiſtrate is not to uſe his Sword in Religious affairs, is (though in ſome ſenſe true, and what in that truth may be ſpoken) in the groſs obnoxious to miſtake through the want of conſideriug what the matter <hi>(materia circa quam)</hi> of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Empire is, which is the outward acts of men only (thoſe Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious acts I ſay, as well as Secular, that are outward) and the not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhing in the government of the Church aright, between that which Chriſt hath committed to the Magiſtrate, and what he keeps in his own hands, and executes by his own officers. That which is therefore rather to be ſaid, to build Uniformly on the ſame bottom, I ſuppoſe is this; The Magiſtrate in that Author's notion is God's chief Officer to ſee his revealed Will in the world, and as a Chriſtian Magiſtrate let me ſay, to ſee his will in the Church to be performed.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:94656:14"/>This I take it (underſtanding it as to mens outward acts, and without an excluſive meaning of his determining power in indifferent things) is very well. Now it is the will of God, that every man alwayes in what he acts (though he is not alwayes to act) whether in things Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious or Civil ſhould do according to his Conſcience, ſo far for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, as never to do againſt it; which he requires of him under thoſe terms, that <hi>he ſhall ſin</hi> certainly if he does. This is God's will by the light of Nature, by the rule of Scripture, and univerſal Conſent. The Conſcience either <hi>is in the Right,</hi> and then it is as God to us, it muſt be obeyed, we muſt do according to it, we ought not to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed by man: Or it <hi>is in an Error,</hi> and then we muſt not go againſt it, even when we are bound to be informed otherwiſe, and lay down that Error. It is the duty conſequently of the Magiſtrate to ſee that his Subjects be not put upon any thing that is againſt their Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, and that they ſerve God (when it is fit) according to them. If a man goes againſt his Conſcience, I ſay <hi>he ſins</hi> againſt God, which it is his will he ſhould not do; and how does that man ſee the will of God to be executed, who compels men to that, the contrary whereof is his Will?</p>
            <p>There is no need here, to put any difference between thoſe things that do not differ in this point. Let the Magiſtrate under the <hi>Goſpel</hi> have <hi>the ſame</hi> power with thoſe (allowing a variety only in their Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cials) under the <hi>Law.</hi> And whether things are <hi>Religious,</hi> or <hi>Secular,</hi> if God hath left them free, and neither preſcribed nor forbidden them, let ſuch be equally at the Magiſtrates determination, with this differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence alone, that God hath determined more things certainly (if not all things but Circumſtances only) in <hi>Religion,</hi> (and ſo exempted <hi>them</hi> from humane arbitriment) then he hath done in <hi>Civil</hi> matters. Let the Magiſtrate know farther, That in whatſoever he may Command, his Power is coercive, and his Sword may be uſed (I ſpeak as to the <hi>Quod licet,</hi> not <hi>quid convenit</hi>) to cauſe his own, and much more God's Will, to be done. There is nothing of all this does hurt that Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty I ſtate, and eſtabliſh for the Conſcience, whoſe ſafeguard I place not in any diſtinction in reference to the Magiſtrates power, between things <hi>Sacred</hi> and <hi>Civil,</hi> or between what might or ought to be done under the Law, and may not under the Goſpel: but in the moſt holy Anchor of God's ſupream Authority and determination, which over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rules the Magiſtrate, who derives from, and muſt not go againſt his Will; nor can command or compel to that which he hath made to <hi>be ſin,</hi> as the doing any thing againſt Conſcience is. <hi>Duo ſunt genera
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:94656:14"/>actnum imperil qui ar jus imperantis non pertinent, Deo vetita jubers, Deo juſſa vetare.</hi> And unto this is there nothing moreover (that I know of) to be added or replied, but only to decide well (as is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timated from Divines at the firſt) between <hi>Reſtraint</hi> and <hi>Conſtraint,</hi> if I may ſo ſpeak; it being one thing I mean how far the Magiſtrate may proceed in <hi>reſtraining</hi> men of wild Principles that they act nor accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their Conſcience (miſ-inflamed) and another in <hi>conſtraining</hi> them to do things which are againſt their Conſcience. That the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate may proceed in the one, that is to <hi>reſtraint</hi> upon good reaſon, it appears from hence; becauſe that although God does require every man to act in whatſoever he does according to his Conſcience, yet he requires not that in every thing, which is according to his Conſcience, he ſhould act. His Conſcience may be erroneous, or the thing not expedient, if lawful to be done. Again, the Magiſtrates Conſcience and his are two; He may think he is bound in Conſcience to act (ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in preaching Seditious or ſeducing Doctrine) yet if upon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint he acts not, his Conſcience cannot accuſe him of ſin, becauſe he cannot help it, and the Magiſtrates reſtraining him is (according as he believes) good, and thereupon he does it. Now here is nothing contrary to his office, the <hi>execution of God's Will</hi> (whoſe <hi>Miniſter</hi> he is) for the man, I ſay, does not break his Will (though his Will be, if he act, he ſhould act according to his Conſcience) becauſe that beſides the thing perhaps is not to be done, he is under reſtraint; and ſo excuſed even to himſelf by the neceſſity: and the Magiſtrate does perform his <hi>Will</hi> (as he judges) in reſtraining him, becauſe of the evil that would follow if he ſhould ſuffer him. But now in the caſe of <hi>Conſtraint,</hi> I mean in the conſtraining any to do that which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their Conſcience, that is, manifeſtly againſt the office or work of the Magiſtrate, who being to ſee God's Will performed, does hereby directly endeavour that his Will be not performed. His Will is, that the man ſhould never act againſt his Conſcience whatſoever comes of it, and he is forcing him hereunto.</p>
            <p>Here then are there <hi>two Queſtions,</hi> in thoſe Papers mentioned, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to the life, as the ſum of what could be deſired, if they had but been directly anſwered when propoſed. The one is, <hi>How far men must be ſuffered to do thoſe things which they ſay they are in Conſcience ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to do?</hi> The other is, <hi>How far they may be commanded and enforced to do ſuch things which they indeed believe, and ſay, they are in Conſcience abliged not to do?</hi> The ſubſtance of theſe Queſtions, I perceive that excelling Gentleman takes to be one, and ſo they are paſſed off into
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:94656:15"/>his main entendment. But as the putting a difference (I accounted before) as to ſome things which (in relation to what is aſſerted) ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits none: So muſt the confounding that here, wherein the difference being put is ſo much to purpoſe, needs lead unto darkneſs. To theſe two Queſtions therefore I anſwer in the ſtead of thoſe Papers. As to the <hi>former,</hi> I doubt not but men may and ought to be reſtrained oftentimes in many things unto which they think themſelves to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged; and my ground for it is given. As to the <hi>latter,</hi> I humbly do apprehend that in that point alone, the Liberty which theſe ſaid Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers have ſo ingeniouſly contended for, is to be placed: and ſo far an that comes to, the Arguments they have tendred are prevailing. It is not becauſe a man's acts barely are <hi>Religious,</hi> that I plead an exempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the Magiſtrate as is ſtill ſaid, but becauſe of his <hi>Conſcience:</hi> Whether the acts be Religious, Moral, or Civil, the man makes a Conſcience of them, and the Sword cannot reach to the inward-man, or to the Conſcience. It does not me dole we know with mens inward acts at all, and it cannot reach I ſay to compel outward acts againſt the Conſcience, becauſe that were to uſe the Sword againſt God, and the Magiſtrate is <hi>the Miniſter of God.</hi> But it may reach to hinder or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain outward acts which ſome men are about doing, or think they ought to do according to their Conſciences, becauſe their Conſcience or judgment may deceive them; And either the thing ought a or to be done, or it may not be fit to be done; If it be fit for themſelves, it may not in regard of others, or the publick utility; unto which they are to give place.</p>
            <p>Let me yet uſe a few more words (I crave pardon I have uſed ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny) for while words are onely to make the mind known, I may expreſs my ſelf ill; but no words are enough, though multiplied, till that be done. Where the Conſcience is erroneous, I ſay, Gods will lies in both theſe things, That a man ſhould not do <hi>againſt</hi> his Conſcience, becauſe it is his Conſcience; and that he ſhould not do <hi>according</hi> to his Conſcience, becauſe it is erroneous; but that he ſhould lay down his Error, and ſo act. And this is the meaning of that which Divines do ſay, That ſuch a Conſcience does <hi>ligare, non obligare.</hi> The Magiſtrate accordingly may not compel him to that which is <hi>poſitive,</hi> to act againſt his Conſcience; but to that which is <hi>negative,</hi> to wit, not to act ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to it. Put a caſe in this point as high as you can any: Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a man, who is otherwiſe a very conſciencious man, hath imbibed ſuch ill-ſhapen Fifth-Monarchy-Principles, that he cannot own the preſent Powers that are over him, and ſo dare not do any thing, in the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:94656:15"/>doing whereof he ſhall own them; what ſhall the moſt tender Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate do with ſuch men, unleſs as we do with Wolves and wild Creatures, that is, lock them up that they may do no hurt? I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, The Magiſtrate, I think, cannot compel this Fifth-Monarchy-man to any ſuch actual owning of his Authority, or to any ſuch act whereby he owns him, that does go againſt his Conſcience, (he cannot compel a man to own the true God or Chriſt, contrary to his Light;) but if he act according to his Conſcience, in diſowning the Powers, ſpeaking againſt them, reſiſting or rebelling, he may be puniſhed too, juſtly, upon the ſame reaſon; becauſe though it be Gods will a man ſhould never act againſt his Conſcience, yet it is Gods will too, that he ſhould not act according to it, when it is erroneous and wicked, and for ſo doing, he is puniſhed. The ſum is, The Magiſtrate may not many times uſe his Sword in the <hi>Poſitives,</hi> when he may in the <hi>Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives</hi> of his Commands or Laws, which he exerts and enforces as Gods Miniſter for the putting the Divine Will in execution. And after this, I am very glad methinks, to find the Teſtimony of two ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as I do to this Determination. <hi>Suſpenſo pede hic incedendum, ut illi lpſi qui Divinae humanae<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ordinationi reſiſtunt, non tam cogantur bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facere, quam malefacere prohibeantur; Quae duo in hot ipſo argumento, Magustinus olim</hi> (Con. Petil. l. 2. c. 83.) <hi>provide diſtinxi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> Grotius de Imp. Cir. ſac. c. 6. ſ. 10.</p>
            <p>To draw then to an end. In things agreeable to common Light; and the natural Good of Mankind, this coercive power of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate lies open. In things Religious, whether indifferent or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, the uſe of the ſame Power appears juſtifiable, upon the ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition that they are not againſt the Conſciences of thoſe on whom they are impoſed (as the ſervice of the true God we are to ſuppoſe was not againſt any of the Jews Conſciences (or at leaſt in their account was not) when the good Kings in the time of the Law compelled them to it) but if the Magiſtrate be inform'd that any thing either is in its na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or becomes grievous to the Conſciences of his People, the caſe is alter'd. He may apply other Remedies, as a Chriſtian; but as a Magiſtrate he may not, upon the account declared, compel any body to that, the doing whereof is ſin to him, and ſo againſt Gods will that he ſhould do it. I will adde, Power in the Root (which in my Papers that lie by, is made out) is nothing elſe but Gods will that ſuch a man ſhould command: But in theſe things which God hath prohibited, it is not his will that any ſhould command, and much leſs uſe coercion alſo. Conſequently; if the Magiſtrate command a thing againſt my
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:94656:16"/>Conſcience, that Command (at leaſt to me) is void, and without power. Gods Vicegerent within me, my Conſcience, makes his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Voice to ceaſe. So far as his power goes then, we may grant it to be coercive; but in things againſt the Conſcience, he indeed hath not any; who muſt ſay hereof, what <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid of the Truth, <hi>I can do nothing againſt it,</hi> but <hi>for</hi> it, and <hi>according</hi> to it.</p>
            <p>I remember in the Life of <hi>Joſephus,</hi> when ſome of the <hi>Trachonites</hi> came in for reſcue to the Jews, where himſelf was Governour, and the Jews would thereupon conſtrain them to be circumcized, or elſe let them not abide with them; he would not permit that injurious Zeal, alledging, <hi>That every man ought according to his own Mind, and not by mans compulſion, to ſerve God.</hi> In our Engliſh Story (to ſuit this) when <hi>Ethelbert</hi> the firſt Prince that received Chriſtianity of the Saxon Hep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarchy, was converted by <hi>Austin,</hi> ſent hither by <hi>Gregory,</hi> and many thereupon came into the Church, it is ſaid, <hi>He ſpecially embraced thoſe that came in, but compelled none; for he had learned that the Faith and Service of Chriſt ought to be voluntary and not of conſtraint. It helpeth much to eſtabliſh the publick Tranquility</hi> (ſays the Imperial Edict of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantine</hi> and <hi>Licinius</hi>) <hi>for every man to have liberty to uſe and chuſe what kind of worſhipping himſelf pleaſes: And for that intent is this done of us, to have no man inforced to one Religion more than another.</hi> A Prince <hi>who would draw his ſubjects, divided into ſects and factions, to his Religion, ſhould not in my Opinion uſe Force,</hi> ſays <hi>Bodin.</hi> Which he enhaunces more particularly from the Example of <hi>Theodoſius</hi> toward the <hi>Arrians. John Barclay</hi> (not <hi>William</hi> that wrot <hi>Adverſus Monarchomachos</hi>) hath a diſcourſe on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to this effect, about the <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> (as it is thought) under the Name of the <hi>Hyperephanians,</hi> in one Chapter of his <hi>Argenis. It was obſerved by the Popes Councel</hi> (ſays <hi>Guiccardine) that the Proſecution of</hi> Luther, <hi>ſince it was not accompanied with their own Reformation, did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe his Reputation: and that it had been a leſs evil to diſſemble the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of ſuch a matter, which would perhaps have diſſolved of its ſelf, than by blowing at the Brand, to make the Fire burn the more.</hi> There are ſome Notes may be conferred with this out of <hi>Davilah,</hi> upon the Delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the politick <hi>Katharine</hi> Regent of <hi>France,</hi> about the Pacifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in her Son <hi>Henry</hi> the Ill's time; I will reſt in one, after <hi>Hexry</hi> the IV. ſucceeded: That great Prince thought good to declare himſelf Catholick, but gets that ſame Edict for Liberty to the <hi>Hugonots,</hi> to be renewed and paſſed the Parliament of <hi>Paris;</hi> by which means endeavouring to remove ſuſpition from their minds, and confirming them by good uſage, together with ſome Gifts and Promiſes to the chief
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:94656:16"/>Heads, he inſenſibly took away (ſays that Hiſtorian) the pulſe and ſtrength of that Party; ſo that thoſe that are verſed in the Kingdom, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that a few years of ſuch ſweet poyſon (if he had not been diſabled in this courſe through want of money) would have extinguiſhed that Faction, which ſo many years of deſperate War, had not, with the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of ſo much blood, been able to weaken. <hi>Violent Courſes,</hi> ſays my Lord <hi>Cook, are like hot Waters, that may do good in an extremity; but the uſe of them doth ſpoyl the Stomach, and it will require them ſtronger and ſtronger, and by little and little they will leſſen the operation. They that love this Commonwealth,</hi> ſays Judge <hi>Jenkins, will uſe means, together with the Reſtitution of the King, to procure an Act of Oblivion, and Tender Conſciences a juſt and reaſonable ſatisfaction, elſe we must all periſh, firſt or laſt.</hi> I ſet down theſe paſſages which my ſelf occaſionally have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: I might add many more out of others. But let the mouth of all mortal Suffrage be ſtopt from henceforward, ſince we have a determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation from the Metropolitan Chair; and the Oracle, in that Book which is the Subject of the precedent <hi>Animadverſions,</hi> hath thus ſpoken, <hi>The Voice of the publick Laws cannot but drown the uncertain Whiſpers of a tender Conſcience; all its ſcruples are huſht and ſilenc'd by the Commands of Authority; it dares not whimper, when that forbids; and the nod of a Prince awes it into ſilence and ſubmiſſion. But if they dare murmur, they muſt be chaſtized out of their peeviſhneſs, and laſh'd into obedience.</hi> Unto which I muſt ſubjoyn this for ſurpluſage; <hi>And theſe things</hi> (ſays he) <hi>cannot but appear with an undeniable evidence to any man that is not invincibly either ignorant or wilful, or both; and therefore 'tis time they ſhould, at leaſt for ſhame, if they will not for Conſcience, ceaſe to diſturb the Church with Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours and Exceptions ſo miſerably impertinent, that I bluſh for having th<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> far purſued them with a ſerious Confutation.</hi> So let us leave that <hi>Here</hi> to his Victory, in the <hi>Sella Curulis</hi> of his own Imagination.</p>
            <p>Sound Drums and Trumpets. <hi>Exit</hi> the brave Author:</p>
            <p>One carrying off the Slain. <hi>Vos Epiſcopi plaudite.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 4. <hi>line</hi> 10. <hi>read,</hi> the Inſtance of the Cottage, with a Parentheſis. <hi>p.</hi> 8. <hi>l.</hi> 17. <hi>f.</hi> bound to the King, <hi>r.</hi> bound to the thing.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
